<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="85"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                    AREA VI – Extension and Community Involvement

             PARAMETER A – PRIORITIES AND RELEVANCE

                I.  SYSTEMS – INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                  The Institution has an approved Extension Agenda.

                                    Rule X Extension Operation Article 1. Organizational Philosophy

                       Section 5.  Thrusts – Extension projects and other activities are in accord with the identified
                       Research, Development and Extension (RD & E) thrusts.  These are:

                                 Poverty alleviation;
                                 Food security;
                                 Primary health care and public health;
                                 Alternative medicine;
                                 Cultural heritage preservation;
                                 Ecosystem management;
                                 Energy conservation and utilization;
                                 Institutional capability building;
                                 Information and communication technology;
                                 Infrastructure planning and design;
                                 Bio-technology
                                 Industrial technology
                                 Pedagogy/Andragogy;
                                 Gender and development;
                                 Coffee;
                                 Pineapple;
                                 Banana;
                                 Kaong;
                                 Makapuno;
                                 Herbs and spices; and
                                 Ornamentals

                  The Institution has an approved Extension Manual

                                 Excerpt from CvSU Manual of Operation – Rule X Extension Operation
                               University Mandate on Extension Services – Extension Services is an outreach
                       unit of the Cavite State University.  As mandated, the University shall “provide advanced
                       instruction and professional training in agriculture, science and technology, education and
                       other related fields, undertake research and extension services, and provide progressive
                       leadership  in  these  areas.”  (Republic  Act  No.  8468,  converting  the  Don  Severino
                       Agricultural College into University Status, to be called Cavite State University).

                       Article 1.  Organizational Philosophy
                               Section  1.    Vision  –  “Alleviating  the  standard  of  living  of  the  economically  and
                       socially disadvantaged sectors of society.”

                               Section  2.    Mission  –  “To  engage  in  the  improvement  of  the  quality  of  life  of
                       farmers/fishermen, women, out-of-school youths, local government employees, and other
                       clients through the conduct of relevant education and training; farm and business advisory





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       1]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                       services;  demonstration  services;  and  information,  communication  and  technology
                       services.”
                               Section 3.  Goals

                               a.  Promote and disseminate innovative, relevant, appropriate and research-based
                                  knowledge, information and technologies to various clients;

                               b.  Engage  and  enhance  partnership  with  various  stakeholders,  local  and
                                  international to address the needs of the target clients and the communities, and
                                  the resource limitation of the extension organization; and

                               c.  Enhance  the  organization’s  capability  to  provide  excellent  and  world-class
                                  extension services.


                               Section 4.  Objectives

                               a.  To conduct and/or coordinate relevant training programs and short non-degree
                                  courses in agriculture and other disciplines;

                               b.  To promote agricultural entrepreneurship and other business enterprises;

                               c.  To establish and maintain on-campus and off-campus demonstration projects
                                  showcasing various appropriate technologies;

                               d.  To   package     and    disseminate    through    tri-media    the   needed
                                  technology/information  relevant  to  the  improvement  of  the  farming  and
                                  rural/urban living;

                               e.  To coordinate and monitor the extension activities of various colleges and branch
                                  campuses of the University;

                               f.  To  collaborate  and  establish  linkages  with  government  and  private  agencies
                                  engaged in extension and rural/urban development in the pursuit of common
                                  goals and objectives; and

                               g.  To  generate  income  from  established  projects  and  from  other  resource
                                  generation activities.

























                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       2]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  The institution has an approved Organizational Structure of the Extension Program





























































                    Prepared by:                 Reviewed by:                        Approved:


                    RITCH M. BANATE              MILDRED A. SEBASTIAN                NOEL A. SEDIGO
                    Extension Coordinator        Campus Coordinator                  Campus Administrator












                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT




                      There is a pool of consultants/experts for extension activities.









































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       4]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                II.  IMPLEMENTATION

                  There is complementation of the curricular/program and the extension projects/activities

                           The population explosion in Brgy. Bagtas has led to an initiative to alleviate poverty in

                    the barangay.  Brgy. Bagtas, having the most number of populations in Tanza (20,370 out of
                    188,755),  has  been  the  site  for  relocation  and  reclamation.    However,  people,  who  were
                    displaced out of their previous addresses, were relocated in the said barangay without having
                    a regular source of living.  Some of them could not find a decent job because they lack the

                    educational and other requirements for the job that they were applying for.  Others could not
                    start any business because they lack the skills in preparing innovative products that could help

                    them earn additional income for their families. Thus, different extension activities are being
                    proposed  to  increase  the  quality  of  life  of  the  citizens  in  the  said  barangay.    Non-formal
                    education will help out-of-school children to be able to read, write and count and also help the

                    out-of-school youths and adults to finish their secondary education.  Also, livelihood programs
                    deemed to strengthen housewives skills and at the same time, augment the meager income of

                    their families. The university’s extension program dubbed as “Bagtas ay Aasenso at Giginhawa
                    kung Tayo Ay Sama-sama with CvSU –Tanza” (BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza).
                           The Teacher Education Department of Cavite State University – Tanza Campus aims to

                    make positive impact to the community. The said department is composed of two units, the
                    Bachelor  of  Secondary  Education  and  Elementary.  But  with  regards  to  the  commitment  in
                    providing extension services, the two units work hand in hand to attain a common goal. The

                    department launched its Computer Literacy Program in order to help initialize the BAGTAS
                    with CvSU-Tanza program. The goal of the program is to  increase computer literacy in the
                    adopted community through trainings and classes.


                    Extension services conducted by the Teacher Education Department based on its course
                    offering in the last 3 years:
                                                                                    Bachelor of Information
                                 Date                     Title of Activity          Technology Courses
                                                                                         Complement
                             ON-GOING               Computer Literacy Classes        DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                          to ALS Students                  Computing
                                                                                   CCTN 50 Basic Computer
                                                                                        Troubleshooting
                                                                                  ITEC 70 Multimedia System
                                                                                  ITEC 75 Technopreneurship
                                                                                     ITEC 101 E-Commerce
                       February 6 and 11, 2020      Microsoft Office Application     DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                      (Excel) Training to ALS              Computing
                                                             Students
                      February 20 and 27, 2020      Microsoft Office Application     DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                      (Word) Training to ALS               Computing
                                                             Students



                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                            May 11, 2018                  Basic Computer             DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                       Troubleshooting and                 Computing
                                                           Maintenance             CCTN 50 Basic Computer
                                                                                        Troubleshooting
                                                                                  ITEC 70 Multimedia System
                             May 4, 2018             Graphic Design and Basic        DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                             Animation                     Computing
                                                                                       DCIT 22 Computer
                                                                                         Programming I
                                                                                   CCTN 50 Basic Computer
                                                                                        Troubleshooting
                                                                                  ITEC 70 Multimedia System
                            April 20, 2018                Basic Computer             DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                       Troubleshooting and                 Computing
                                                           Maintenance                 DCIT 22 Computer
                                                                                         Programming I
                                                                                   CCTN 50 Basic Computer
                                                                                        Troubleshooting
                                                                                  ITEC 70 Multimedia System
                           October 28, 2017         Computer Literacy Program        DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                       for Barangay Officials              Computing
                                                       (MS Office Tutorials)          DCIT 24 Information
                                                                                          Management
                           October 27, 2017         Computer Literacy Program        DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                       for Barangay Officials              Computing
                                                       (MS Office Tutorials)          DCIT 24 Information
                                                                                          Management
                           October 21, 2017         Computer Literacy Program        DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                       for Barangay Officials              Computing
                                                       (MS Office Tutorials)          DCIT 24 Information
                                                                                          Management
                           October 20, 2017         Computer Literacy Program        DCIT 21 Introduction to
                                                       for Barangay Officials              Computing
                                                       (MS Office Tutorials)          DCIT 24 Information
                                                                                          Management
                  The  institution  follows  the  Process  of  development  of  the  institutional  extension
                    program/agenda

                                               Rule X Extension Operation Art. 10
                            Policies, Guidelines, and Procedures. Art. 11 Monitoring and Evaluation

                    Section 2.  Formulation of Research, Development and Extension Agenda and Program
                    (RDEAP)

                           CvSU-RDEAP evolved through the following integrated and participatory processes:

                           a.  RECETS conducts planning workshop.  The Research, Extension and Continuing
                               Education  and  Training  Services  (RECETS)  headed  by  the  Vice  President
                               spearheads the formulation of the RDEAP through a workshop.  Participants in this
                               planning workshop are the Deans of the different Colleges and branch campuses
                               together  with  their  respective  Research,  Development  and  Extension  (RDE
                               Coordinators.





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       6]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                           b.  During the University planning workshop the thrusts of the University are reviewed
                               and revised.  In this process, identification and selection of research and extension
                               thrusts are guided by the stated vision and mission of the university/college/campus.
                               Likewise,  the  Millennium  Development  Goals  (MDGs),  national  and  provincial,
                               municipal and local development goals are considered.

                           c.  The research, development and extension (RDE) thrusts resulting from the latest
                               (2004)  RDEAP  planning  workshops  include:  poverty  alleviation,  food  security,
                               primary  health  care  and  public  health,  alternative  medicine,  cultural  heritage
                               preservation,  ecosystem  management,  energy  conservation  and  utilization,
                               institutional  capability  building,  information  and  communication  technology,
                               infrastructure  planning  and  design,  bio-technology,  industrial  technology,
                               pedagogy/andragogy, gender and development, coffee, pineapple, banana, kaong,
                               makapuno, herbs and spices, ornamentals, and urban agriculture.


                    Section 3.  Presentation of RDEAP by College

                       a.  Prior to the actual conduct of RDEAP planning workshop, the RDE Coordinators present
                           their  draft  plans  with  their  respective  Deans  for  further  comments  and  suggestions.
                           During the workshop, the RDE Coordinators polish their prepared Agenda.  As part of
                           the  workshop,  the  RDEAP  of the  different  Colleges/Campuses  are  presented to  the
                           RECETS Council for comments and suggestions.

                           Also,  during  the  presentation  of  various  agenda  and  programs  by  College/Campus,
                           duplication  of  plans  and  programs  are  eliminated.    In  cases  where  similar  areas  of
                           concerns are presented by two or more Colleges, either one party will drop its proposed
                           knowledge area or integrate such with the others of similar nature.  Also, group members
                           openly  discuss  and  decide  as  to  who  would  lead  in  the  implementation  of  such
                           programs.

                       b.  Deans  endorse  the  corrected  copy  of  their  RDEAPs  to  Research  Center  for
                           consolidation.    RDE  Coordinators  incorporate  the  comments  and  suggestions  made
                           during the presentation.  The Deans submit the corrected copy to the Research Center
                           Council for consolidation.

                             Research Center collects the RDEAPs of the different colleges.  The RDEAP
                               sod the different colleges/campuses are consolidated by Research Center into one
                               University RDEAP for the final review of the RECETS Council members.

                             RECETS  Council  endorses  the  University  RDEAP  to  the  Administrative
                               Council.  The RECETS Council through the VP-RECETS, who chairs the council,
                               endorses  the  RDEAP  to  the  Administrative  Council  for  approval  of  the  Board  of
                               Regents.

                             Administrative Council endorses and recommends for approval of RDEAP to
                               the Board of Regents.

                             BOT approves the RDEAP

                             RECETS provides the approved RDEAP to concerned offices.

                    Section 4.  Preparation of Extension Project Proposals



                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                         Call for capsule proposals.  Office of the Director for Extension calls for the submission
                           of  an  extension  proposal  following  the  format  of  funding  agencies.    The  Extension
                           Services has its own format for extension proposal.

                         College/Campuses prepare capsule proposals.   Faculty members of the different
                           colleges with varied fields of specialization prepare capsule proposal on their areas of
                           expertise  and  interest.    The  proposal  maybe  singly  prepared  or  in  cooperation
                           (interdisciplinary approach) with other extensionists.  The proposals are in line with the
                           approved  RDEAP.    Capsule  proposals  are  reviewed  at  the  department  level  to  the
                           college levels by the respective research and extension committee in coordination with
                           RDE Coordinator.

                         Deans  endorse  capsule  proposals  to  RECETS  Council  through  the  Extension
                           Director.  The reviewed proposals are then endorsed to the RECETS Council through
                           the Director for approval.

                         RECETS Council reviews and approves the capsule proposals.  All the extension
                           proposals  must  be  reviewed  and  approved  by  the  RECETS  Council  prior  to  their
                           implementation.

                         RECETS  endorses  the  approved  proposals  for  University  or  external  funding.
                           Proposals requiring bigger funding are usually submitted to external funding institution
                           while the remaining projects are scheduled for local funding.

                         RECETS  prepares  work  and  financial  plans  for  approved  projects.    Extension
                           Director considers the newly approved proposals in the preparation of their annual work
                           and financial plan.

                    Section 5. Implementation of Approved Projects

                       a)  Proponents  implement  their  approved  projects  following  their  scheduled
                           activities.    Program/project  leaders  implement  their  approved  projects  at  their
                           respective colleges/campuses in coordination with RECETS.  While the University has
                           RECETS that is in-charge of the research and extension functions, the planning and
                           implementation of research and extension projects is decentralized but unified up to the
                           department level.  This approach has been institutionalized and exemplified in CvSU
                           through the concept we called UGNAYAN.


                    Article 11. Monitoring and Evaluation

                       a)  Monitoring continuously tracks performance against what was planned by collecting
                           and  analyzing  data  on  the  indicators  established  for  monitoring  and  evaluation
                           purposes.  It provides continuous information on whether progress is being made toward
                           achieving results (outputs, outcomes and goals) through record keeping and regular
                           reporting  systems.    Monitoring  looks  at  both  programme  processes  and  changes  in
                           conditions of target groups and institutions brought about by programme activities.  It
                           also identifies strengths and weaknesses in a programme.  The performance information
                           generated from monitoring enhances learning from experience and improves decision-
                           making.  Management and programme implementers typically conduct monitoring.
                           Evaluation is a periodic, in-depth analysis of programme performance.  In relies on data
                           generated  through  monitoring  activities  as  well  as  information  obtained  from  other
                           sources (e.g., studies, research, in-depth interviews, focus group discussions, surveys
                           etc.). Evaluations are often (but not always) conducted with the assistance of external
                           evaluators (UNFPA, 2004).



                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       8]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE



                  The stakeholders participate in the formulation of the Extension Agenda

                       The extension programs of CvSU – Tanza Campus is based upon the extension agenda of
                       the main campus, which in turn is based on the regional and national development thrust
                       and direction. The BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza program is also based on the result of an
                       extensive community needs assessment conducted by the campus at Barangay Bagtas,
                       Tanza,  Cavite.  Different  stakeholders  participated  during  the  formulation  of  Extension
                       Agenda.
                                  STAKEHOLDERS                                 PARTICIPATION


                        Administration                           Participates  in  the  planning  and  provide
                                                                 necessary  budget  for  implementation  of
                                                                 extension projects.
                        Campus                                   Prepares     Research      and      Extension
                                                                 Agenda/Programs
                        Department of Management                 Initiates the “Livelihood Programs” activities
                                                                 and projects.
                        Department         of      Information  Initiates  the  “Computer  Literacy  Program”
                        Technology                               activities and projects.
                        Teacher Education Department             Initiates  the  “Oplan  Karunungan”  activities
                                                                 and projects.
                        Student Organization of Education Unit  Provides  assistance  in  different  extension
                                                                 activities    including     planning      and
                                                                 implementation
                        Local Government Unit - Tanza            Coordinates  with  other  government  agencies
                                                                 and  non-government  organization  for  support
                                                                 and  assistance  to  ensure  the  success  of  the
                                                                 program.
                        Barangay  Chairperson  of  Bagtas,  Participates in the planning process and would
                        Tanza, Cavite                            provide venue for different activity.
                        Barangay  Residents  particularly  non- Participate  in  different  activities  such  as
                        working  women,  out-of-school  youths,  planning,  implementation,  evaluation,  and
                        out-of-school   children   and    4P’s  monitoring of the program, would serve as the
                        members.                                 beneficiary of the program.




















                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                       9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  The  Institution’s  Extension  Program/Agenda  for  the  program  under  survey  is  presented  as
                    follows:
























































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      10]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE




                III.  OUTCOMES

                  Priority and relevant extension projects and activities are conducted.

                                 Date                     Title of Activity                  Venue
                             ON-GOING                Computer Literacy Classes        Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                          to ALS Students
                       February 6 and 11, 2020      Microsoft Office Application      Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                      (Excel) Training to ALS
                                                             Students
                      February 20 and 27, 2020      Microsoft Office Application      Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                       (Word) Training to ALS
                                                             Students
                            May 11, 2018                  Basic Computer              Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                        Troubleshooting and
                                                           Maintenance
                             May 4, 2018             Graphic Design and Basic         Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                             Animation
                            April 20, 2018                Basic Computer              Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                        Troubleshooting and
                                                           Maintenance
                           October 28, 2017         Computer Literacy Program         Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                       for Barangay Officials
                                                        (MS Office Tutorials)

                           October 27, 2017         Computer Literacy Program         Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                       for Barangay Officials
                                                        (MS Office Tutorials)

                           October 21, 2017         Computer Literacy Program         Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                       for Barangay Officials
                                                        (MS Office Tutorials)

                           October 20, 2017         Computer Literacy Program         Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                       for Barangay Officials
                                                        (MS Office Tutorials)




























                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  The extension activity is conducted in partnership with Brgy. Bagtas through a Memorandum of
                    Agreement.





















































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT



























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      14]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT



























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  The extension activity has a long-term plan for its smooth conduct.



















































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  The extension activity is approved by the University Board of Regents.





















































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      18]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                                Republic of the Philippines
                                              CAVITE STATE UNIVERSITY
                                                      Tanza Campus
                                     Ph. 2, Bahay Katuparan, Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                    (046) 235 – 7997
                                                    www.cvsu.edu.ph




                                            EXTENSION PROJECT PROPOSAL


             I.   Project Description

                  Title           :   BAGTAS with CvSU-Tanza


                                      (Bagtas ay Aasenso at Giginhawa kung Tayo Ay Sama-sama with
                                      CvSU -Tanza)

                  Location        :   Brgy. Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite

                  Proponent       :   Cavite State University – Tanza Campus

                  Beneficiaries  :    Out-of-school Children and Youth, Brgy. Officials, and non-working
                                         members of the community

                  Project Components:

                           Program 1:  Oplan Karunungan
                           Program 2:   Computer Literacy for Brgy. Officials
                           Program 3:   Livelihood Programs for Non-Working Members of the Community

                           Program 4:   Health and Wellness
                  Partner Agencies:  Local Government Unit of the Municipality of Tanza, Cavite; Provincial
                                          Cooperative, Livelihood, and Entrepreneurial Development Office
                                          (PCLEDO); Farmers Training Center (FITS); Companies in Export
                                          Processing Zone Authority (EPZA)

                  Estimated Budget: Php 610,000

                  Duration        :   5 years

             II.   Rationale      :


                         The population explosion in Brgy. Bagtas has led to an initiative to alleviate poverty in the
                  barangay.    Brgy.  Bagtas,  having  the  most  number  of  populations  in  Tanza  (20,370  out  of
                  188,755), has been the site for relocation and reclamation.  However, people, who were displaced
                  out of their previous addresses, were relocated in the said barangay without having a regular
                  source of living.  Some of them could not find a decent job because they lack the educational and
                  other requirements for the job that they were applying for.  Others could not start any business
                  because they lack the skills in preparing innovative products that could help them earn additional
                  income for their families.




                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE




                         Thus, different extension activities are being proposed to increase the quality of life of the
                  citizens in the said barangay.  Non-formal education will help out-of-school children to be able to
                  read, write and count.  Also, livelihood programs deemed to strengthen housewives skills and at
                  the  same time,  augment the meager  income  of  their families.   In  addition,  awareness  drives
                  concerning health and other GAD-related issues are being proposed to inculcate the importance
                  of appropriate living condition for every member of the community.



             III.   Strategies of Implementation

                  A.  Formation of Committee
                             A committee was formed to study and gather benchmark information on the status,
                      needs, and conditions of selected communities in Tanza, Cavite during the second semester,
                      AY 2014 – 2015.  The committee was headed by the Extension Coordinator.  Two faculty
                      members from the different departments of the campus were selected as members of the
                      committee to ensure that the programs will conform to the mandate of the university.  The
                      committee used the following benchmark information, provided by Tanza Municipal Planning
                      and Development Office (TMPDO), in order to assess which group of individuals will be the
                      target beneficiaries of the proposal.

                             Table 1.  Data of Brgy. Bagtas population 2010 by sex, age, and employment
                                                               Male           Female           Total
                               Brgy. Bagtas Population        12,316           8,054          20,370
                               Age Bracket
                                         5 – 9                 1,453             951           2,404
                                        10 – 14                1,299             849           2,148
                                       OTHERS                  9,564           6,254          15,818
                               Enrolment Data
                                   Pre-School (3 – 6)          1,213             878           2,091
                                  Elementary (7 – 12)          1,176             823           1,999
                               Employment Data
                                       Employed                6,908           4,517          11,425
                                      Unemployed                 600             393             993
                                 Not in the labor force        4,808           3,144           7,952
                             Source: Philippine Statistics Authority and Tanza Municipal Planning and Development Office

                             The committee used the descriptive design of a study. Data utilized in the study mainly
                      came from the responses on the self-administered survey questions that were distributed to
                      the residents of Brgy. Bagtas.  Residents were selected using simple random sampling.

                             Results revealed that:

                                  87.14% of the residents perceived that they lack regular sources of living in the
                                    barangay because most (48.15%) of them lack the educational requirements
                                    and some (38.99%) lack the technical skills to either start a small business or
                                    to apply for a regular job;

                                  47.06%  of  the  residents  believed  that  these  problems  and  issues  may  be
                                    addressed through conduct of free seminars/trainings on livelihood programs;



                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      20]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE



                                  18.33% of the residents suggested to conduct free seminar on candle making;
                                    17.33% suggested soap making; 15.33% suggested delicacy preparation such
                                    as yema, ube, leche flan, puto, and others; 13.67% suggested dishwashing
                                    liquid making; 13.00% suggested recycling of plastic products and water lily
                                    bags; while the remaining 8.67% suggested perfume-making;

                                  46.50% of the residents said that they have baking and cooking skills and they
                                    are willing to undergo trainings for delicacy preparation; also 22.50% reiterated
                                    that they  have  the  skills  in  the  arts  and trades and  that  they  are  willing  to
                                    undergo trainings on preparation of innovative products such as candle, soap,
                                    and dishwashing liquid;


                  B.  Preparation of Proposal
                             The proposal to conduct extension programs in the community was based upon the
                      respondent’s needs and interests that are consistent with the goals of the campus and that
                      have been identified through surveys.

                             Some  programs  relative  to  the  needs  and  interests  of  the  residents  were  not
                      considered due to insufficiencies on facilities and absence of qualified faculty members to
                      handle  such  programs.  This  includes  recycling  of  plastic  products,  water  lily  bags,  and
                      perfume-making which may require raw materials that are unavailable from the community.

                             While  having  consultative  meetings  with  the  local  government  of  the  concerned
                      barangay, some requests to the university were raised.  First, the campus will have to offer
                      computer literacy program for their barangay officials.  This program aims to extend computer
                      literacy to the Brgy. officials, who, based on observation, lack with sufficient skills in computer
                      manipulation and processes. The LGU believes that technical skills must be manifested by
                      their officials to better serve their constituents.

                             Also, the LGU requested that the proponents offer literacy skills development among
                      their children.  According to them, a number of children were not enrolled in a formal school
                      and parents of these children affirm that they could not send them in formal school due to lack
                      of financial resources, that although education is free in public schools, they could not provide
                      the requirements that their children must submit.

                             Another request from the LGU is that the proponent should give awareness campaigns
                      on different health issues.  According to them, the increase in the rate of patients with dengue
                      and AIDS/HIV in the province had been alarming them and the residents.  And because the
                      proponent  is  a  GAD  advocate,  GAD-related  issues  and  concerns  were  included  in  this
                      awareness campaign, such as Anti-Violence against Women and their Children (anti-VAWC),
                      sexual harassment among others.


                  C.  Meeting of the Committee
                             A meeting of the campus Committee on Curriculum and Instruction was conducted
                      on April 10, 2015 to deliberate on the proposed extension programs in the campus.

                             The following is the decision of the members of the committee:
                                        Total Number of Committee Members              :      15



                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                        Total Number of Committee Members who
                                               were present                            :      15

                                        Total Number of Committee Members who
                                               were absent                             :      0

                                        Number of Members in favor of the
                                               proposal                                :      15

                                        Number of Members not in favor of the
                                               proposal                                :      0




                             With this result, the following resolutions were passed by the Committee:


                             Resolution No. 3, s. 2015



                                    “Approving  the  extension  project  proposal  to  alleviate  poverty  in  Barangay
                             Bagtas with the following components: (1) Oplan Karunungan; (2) Computer Literacy
                             for Brgy. Officials; (3) Livelihood Programs for the citizens of Brgy. Bagtas; and (4)
                             Health  and  Wellness;  subject  to  the  endorsement  of  the  University  Administrative
                             Council and approval of the University Board of Regents.”
                             Resolution No. 4, s. 2015

                                    “Approving the name of the extension project proposal to be BAGTAS with
                             CvSU-Tanza (Bagtas ay Aasenso at Giginhawa kung Tayo Ay Sama-sama
                             with  CvSU  -Tanza)  subject  to  the  endorsement  of  the  University  Administrative
                             Council and approval of the University Board of Regents.”

                  D.  Memorandum of Agreement
                             A  Memorandum  of  Agreement  (MOA)  will  be  drafted  and  signed  by  different
                      stakeholders involved in the conduct of such extension programs.  Stakeholders such as Local
                      Government Unit of the municipality of Tanza, Cavite; Provincial Cooperative, Livelihood, and
                      Entrepreneurial Development Office (PCLEDO); Farmers Training Center (FITS); Companies
                      in Export Processing Zone Authority (EPZA); and others.

                  E.  Actual Implementation
                             All the extension programs under this project will be spearheaded by the campus dean
                      and  will  be  facilitated  by  faculty  members  and  students  in  their  respective  area  of
                      specialization.  Since this is an extension project, voluntary participation among faculty and
                      students will be encouraged.  Additional funds for the project proposal will be sought through
                      donations  from  the  Local  Government  Unit  of  Brgy.  Bagtas,  Tanza,  Cavite  and  other
                      concerned  citizens  and  government  and  non-government  agencies,  such  as  but  are  not
                      limited  to,  Provincial  Cooperative,  Livelihood,  and  Entrepreneurial  Development  Office
                      (PCLEDO); Farmers Training Center (FITS); Companies in Export Processing Zone Authority
                      (EPZA); and others.





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      22]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                         Program 1: Oplan Karunungan
                         1.  All BSE students and faculty members under the Teacher Education Department are
                             enjoined to take part in this program.
                         2.  The program will be done during Fridays and Saturdays, 7:30 a.m. to 9:30 a.m.at Rm.
                             102 of the Cavite State University – Tanza Campus.
                         3.  The BSE students and faculty members will have their own schedule on when to share
                             their knowledge and teaching skills among the out-of-school youths.
                         4.  For security purposes, each participant will wear name tags during each session to
                             recognize them as part of the program.
                         5.  On the first day of the session, each participant will undergo a pre-assessment to
                             determine their basic literacy and numeracy skills.
                         6.  The officers will coordinate with the Barangay Captain to recommend and/or suggest
                             viable participants of this program.
                         7.  For the first year of implementation, at least 10 out-of-school youths will be the target
                             participants.
                         8.  Assigned members will see to it that cleanliness and orderliness of the said classroom
                             will be maintained during the session.
                         9.  The  teachers  and  student-teachers  will  select  three  best  students  to  be  awarded
                             during the Recognition Program.
                         10. Every participant will be awarded Certificate of Completion upon finishing the
                             program.
                         11. After the program, each participants will undergo a post-assessment to determine the
                             effect of the intervention that was conducted.
                         12. Students who have finished the program will be encouraged and supported to enroll
                             in a formal elementary school.

                         Program 2: Computer Literacy Program
                         1.  All  BSIT  students  and  faculty  members  under  the  Department  of  Information
                             Technology are enjoined to take part in this program.
                         2.  The program will be done during Fridays and Saturdays, 8:30 a.m. to 10:30 a.m. at
                             Computer Laboratory of the Cavite State University – Tanza Campus.
                         3.  The BSIT students and faculty members will have their own schedule on when to share
                             their knowledge and teaching skills among the barangay officials.
                         4.  For security purposes, each participant will wear name tags during each session to
                             recognize them as part of the program.
                         5.  The officers will coordinate with the Barangay Captain to recommend and/or suggest
                             viable participants of this program.
                         6.  For the first year of implementation, at least 10 selected barangay officials and 4P’s
                             members will be taught of basic computer skills during the time allotted.
                         7.  Assigned members will see to it that cleanliness and orderliness of the said
                             classroom will be maintained during the session.
                         8.  The teachers and student-teachers will select three best participants to be awarded
                             during the Recognition Program.
                         9.  Every participant will be awarded Certificate of Completion upon finishing the
                             program.
                         10. As part of the monitoring and evaluation of the program, each participant will undergo
                             a pre- and post-test to determine whether they have achieved the basic skills that are
                             expected of them.

                         Program 3: Livelihood Programs
                         1.  All  BSBM  and  BSHRM  students  and  faculty  members  under  the  Department  of
                             Management are enjoined to take part in this program and will be the facilitators and
                             over-all in-charge.





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                         2.  The program will be done during Fridays and Saturdays, 7:30 a.m. to 9:30 a.m. at
                             Function Hall of the Cavite State University – Tanza Campus.
                         3.  The officers will coordinate with the Barangay Captain to recommend and/or suggest
                             viable participants of this program.
                         4.  Assistance  from  the  Provincial  Cooperative,  Livelihood,  and  Entrepreneurial
                             Development Office (PCLEDO) will be sought in terms of training of participants.
                         5.  At least 20 housewives will be invited to take part in each session.
                         6.  All participants must be residents of Brgy. Bagtas as certified and referred by the LGU
                             officials.
                         7.  Participants  with  outstanding  performance  in  selected  activities  will  be  rewarded
                             accordingly.  They will be given small amount of money to start their own business.
                         8.  Every participant will be awarded Certificate of Completion upon finishing the program.
                         9.  As part of the monitoring and evaluation of the program, each participant will undergo
                             a pre- and post-test to determine whether they have achieved the basic skills that are
                             expected of them.

                         Program 4: Health and Wellness
                         1.  All students and members of the Sports Club of the campus, and faculty members are
                             enjoined to take part in this program.
                         2.  The  Aerobics/Zumba  session  will  be  done  every  Wednesday,  starting  January  to
                             March 2016 thru the initiative of a competitive professional dance instructor. Summer
                             Sports Clinic and Sports fest with the community will be held every weekend starting
                             March to June 2016.  Continuous awareness drive on health issues will be held every
                             Friday  and  Saturday,  starting  January  to  March  2016.   Awareness  drive  on  GAD-
                             related concerns will be held every Wednesday, starting January to March 2016.
                         3.  The officers will coordinate with the Barangay Captain to recommend and/or suggest
                             viable participants of this program.  Also, they will be requested to lend a venue for
                             the program.
                         4.  At least 20 housewives will be invited to take part in the aerobics/Zumba session. Out-
                             of-school youths will be the target participants in the summer sports clinic and sports
                             fest with the community.  At least 30 residents will be the target participants in the
                             awareness drive on health and GAD-related issues.
                         5.  All participants must be residents of Brgy. Bagtas as certified and referred by the LGU
                             officials.
                         6.  Participants  with  outstanding  performance  in  selected  activities  will  be  rewarded
                             accordingly, especially those who exceled in sports and other recreational activities.
                         7.  Every participant will be awarded Certificate of Completion upon finishing the program.
                         8.  As part of the monitoring and evaluation of the program, each participant will undergo
                             a pre- and post-test to determine whether they have achieved the basic skills that are
                             expected of them.

                  F.  Monitoring and Evaluation
                             Each program will undergo three evaluations: before, during, and after conduct of each
                      evaluation.  On the first week of each session, each participant will undergo a pre-assessment
                      to determine their current status in the program they were registered to. Evaluation during the
                      conduct  of  the  program  will  also  be  done  in  order  to  identify  problems  arising  and  to
                      immediately resolve these problems. Post-assessment will be done in order to determine if
                      they  have  achieved  the  basic  skills  that  are  expected  of  them.    This  will  also  determine
                      whether the program is successful and has delivered significant impact to the community.







                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      24]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


             IV.  Budgetary Allocation (5 years)
                                       PARTICULARS/PROGRAM                                 AMOUNT (PhP)

                    Program 1: Oplan Karunungan                                               60,000.00
                    Program 2: Computer Literacy Program                                      45,000.00

                    Program 3: Livelihood Programs for Non-Working Members                    300,000.00
                    of the Community
                    Program 4: Health and Wellness                                           205,000.00

                                              TOTAL                                             610,000.00

             V.   Source of Fund
                         The main source of fund of the project will be the campus budget for extension.  The
                  project proponent will solicit additional funding from the Local Government Unit of Tanza and
                  other partner NGO’s and GO’s such as, but not limited to, Provincial Cooperative, Livelihood, and
                  Entrepreneurial Development Office (PCLEDO); Farmers Training Center (FITS); and Companies
                  in Export Processing Zone Authority (EPZA).



                IV. BEST PRACTICES

                  The Department of Information Technology anchors its Extension Program to the extension
                    thrust/agenda of the University.

                  The extension program has pool of consultants/experts for its extension activities.

                  Stakeholders have active participation in the extension programs of the  Teacher Education
                    Department


                  Through  the  initiative  of  the  Department  of  Information  Technology’s  Computer  Literacy
                    Program, in support with the BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza program, other departments from
                    the campus are now readily anchored with the program.

                  The  Teacher  Education  Department  has  built  a  good  image  among  the  community  before
                    engaging in a full-blown extension program.

                  The Computer Literacy Program are based from an extensive community needs assessment
                    conducted within the barangay.


























                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


             PARAMETER B - PLANNING, IMPLEMENTATION, MONITORING AND EVALUATION

                I.  SYSTEMS – INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                  The institution has an office where the Extension Program is managed.


























                             Mr. Ritch M. Banate, the extension coordinator of Tanza Campus






















                                                Office of Barangay Bagtas




                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      26]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  Participation  of  the  administration,  faculty,  students  and  stakeholders  in  the  planning  of
                    extension projects/activities is evident.

                                                                                       NATURE OF
                        STAKEHOLDERS             PROJECT/ACTIVITY
                                                                             INVOLVEMENT/PARTICIPATION
                        1. Administration    BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza        Participate  in  the  planning  and
                                                                             provide  necessary  budget  for  the
                                                                             implementation    of    extension
                                                                             projects.

                                               COMPUTER LITERACY             Approval  of  different  extension
                                                      PROGRAM                activities  making  sure that  it  is  in
                                                                             accordance  with  the  rules  and
                                                                             regulation of the university.

                                                                             Ensures the strong communication
                                                                             and     commitment       between
                                                                             stakeholders.

                                                                             Spearhead  the  implementation  of
                                                                             “Computer Literacy Program”

                                                                             Ensures the implementation of the
                                                                             program        by       providing
                                                                             faculty/teachers learning modules,
                                                                             trainers,   facilitators,   resource
                                                                             person, etc.

                                                                             Attend  to  meeting  and  other
                                                                             related  activities  regarding  the
                                                                             implementation of the program.

                                                                             Participate in all activities related to
                                                                             planning,         implementation,
                                                                             monitoring  and  evaluation  of  the
                                                                             program.

                                                                             Request    for   a   meeting   to
                                                                             immediately  address  concerns
                                                                             regarding  the  implementation  of
                                                                             the program.
                        2. Faculty (DIT)     BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza        Participates  in  the  planning  for
                                                                             extension services.

                                                                             Supervise the conduct of research
                                               COMPUTER LITERACY             and extension activities.
                                                      PROGRAM
                                                                             Initiate  the  “Computer  Literacy
                                                                             Program”

                                                                             Coordinates between stakeholders
                                                                             regarding the conduct of extension
                                                                             activities.





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                                                             Active   participation   in   the
                                                                             preparation                    of
                                                                             proposal/brochures/program
                                                                             activities/monitoring/evaluation
                                                                             and   needed     documents     for
                                                                             keeping and accreditation.

                                                                             Regular benchmark studies on the
                                                                             profiles  and  needs  of  the  target
                                                                             clients.

                                                                             Support  the  implementation  of
                                                                             “Computer Literacy Program”

                                                                             Prepare  letter  of  request  to
                                                                             conduct  extension  activities  at
                                                                             Barangay Bagtas.

                                                                             Attend  to  meeting  and  other
                                                                             related  activities  regarding  the
                                                                             implementation of the program.

                                                                             Conduct  activities  related  to  the
                                                                             planning,         implementation,
                                                                             monitoring  and  evaluation  of  the
                                                                             extension program.

                                                                             Ensure the safe keeping pertinent
                                                                             files,  document,  materials  and
                                                                             reports regarding the program.


                        3. Students (BSIT)   BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza        Participates  in  the  planning  for
                                                                             extension services.

                                                                             Provide  assistance  in  different
                                               COMPUTER LITERACY             extension    activities   including
                                                      PROGRAM                planning and implementation.
                        4.   Stakeholders    BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza        Participates  in  the  planning  for
                        (LGU-Tanza)                                          extension services.

                                                                             Coordinate with other government
                                               COMPUTER LITERACY             agencies  and  non-government
                                                      PROGRAM                organization  for  support  and
                                                                             assistance to ensure the success
                                                                             of the program.
                        5.     Stakeholder   BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza        Participate in the planning process
                        (Barangay                                            and  would  provide  venue  for
                        Chairperson     of                                   different activity.
                        Bagtas,     Tanza,     COMPUTER LITERACY
                        Cavite)                       PROGRAM
                        6.     Stakeholder   BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza        Participate  in  different  activities
                        (Barangay officials,                                 such as planning, implementation,
                        4P’s    members,




                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      28]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                        out-of-school youth                                  evaluation,  and  monitoring  of  the
                        and  out-of-school     COMPUTER LITERACY             program.
                        children)                     PROGRAM



                  Involvement of administration, faculty and student in the implementation and dissemination of
                    extension programs
                                                                           PERSONS INVOLVED
                         Date              Title of Activity
                                                                Administration       Faculty       Students
                      ON-GOING            Computer Literacy      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.        BYTES
                                           Classes to ALS           Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                               Students                           Ritch M.        Selected IT
                                                                                  Banate           Students
                                                                                  Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo
                  February 6 and 11,       Microsoft Office      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.        BYTES
                         2020             Application (Excel)       Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                           Training to ALS                        Ritch M.        Selected IT
                                               Students                           Banate           Students
                                                                                  Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo
                  February 20 and 27,      Microsoft Office      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.        BYTES
                         2020             Application (Word)        Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                           Training to ALS                        Ritch M.        Selected IT
                                               Students                           Banate           Students
                                                                                  Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine



                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo
                     May 11, 2018          Basic Computer        Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.        BYTES
                                           Troubleshooting          Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                           and Maintenance                        Ritch M.        Selected IT
                                                                                  Banate           Students
                                                                                  Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo
                      May 4, 2018        Graphic Design and      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.        BYTES
                                           Basic Animation          Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                                                                  Ritch M.        Selected IT
                                                                                  Banate           Students
                                                                                  Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo
                     April 20, 2018        Basic Computer        Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.        BYTES
                                           Troubleshooting          Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                           and Maintenance                        Ritch M.        Selected IT
                                                                                  Banate           Students
                                                                                  Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo







                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      30]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                   October 28, 2017       Computer Literacy      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.         COPE
                                             Program for            Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                          Barangay Officials                      Ritch M.        Selected SE
                                              (MS Office                          Banate           Students
                                              Tutorials)                          Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Dr. Noel B.
                                                                                  Manarpiis
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo
                   October 27, 2017       Computer Literacy      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.         COPE
                                             Program for            Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                          Barangay Officials                      Ritch M.        Selected SE
                                              (MS Office                          Banate           Students
                                              Tutorials)                          Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Dr. Noel B.
                                                                                  Manarpiis
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo
                   October 21, 2017       Computer Literacy      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.         COPE
                                             Program for            Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                          Barangay Officials                      Ritch M.        Selected SE
                                              (MS Office                          Banate           Students
                                              Tutorials)                          Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Dr. Noel B.
                                                                                  Manarpiis
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo




                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                   October 20, 2017       Computer Literacy      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.         COPE
                                             Program for            Sedigo        Sebastian       Officers and
                                          Barangay Officials                      Ritch M.        Selected SE
                                              (MS Office                          Banate           Students
                                              Tutorials)                          Joyce Erika
                                                                                  S. Senaris
                                                                                  Cris Albert
                                                                                  P. Cajigas
                                                                                  Debbie Rose
                                                                                  T. Banag
                                                                                  Melona O.
                                                                                  Igmasine
                                                                                  Dr. Noel B.
                                                                                  Manarpiis
                                                                                  Mary Rose
                                                                                  E. Elamparo,
                                                                                  Mark Joel C.
                                                                                  Sibulo


                  There are Extension Projects that are implemented by the Program under survey within the last
                    3-5 years.

                     EXTENSION
                      PROGRAM                     EXTENSION ACTIVITIES                    CLIENT TYPE
                 Bagtas ay Aasenso at         Computer Literacy Classes to ALS               Students
                 Giginhawa kung Tayo                      Students                       Community (4P’s
                  Ay Sama-sama with                                                   members, out-of-school
                     CvSU-Tanza                                                         children, youths and
                 (BAGTAS with CvSU-                                                           adults)
                        Tanza)
                                             Microsoft Office Application (Excel)            Students
                                                  Training to ALS Students               Community (4P’s
                                                                                      members, out-of-school
                                                                                        children, youths and
                                                                                              adults)

                                             Microsoft Office Application (Word)             Students
                                                  Training to ALS Students               Community (4P’s
                                                                                      members, out-of-school
                                                                                        children, youths and
                                                                                              adults)

                                            Basic Computer Troubleshooting and         4P’s members, out-of-
                                                        Maintenance                   school children, youths
                                                                                             and adults

                                            Graphic Design and Basic Animation         4P’s members, out-of-
                                                                                      school children, youths
                                                                                             and adults

                                            Basic Computer Troubleshooting and         4P’s members, out-of-
                                                        Maintenance                   school children, youths
                                                                                             and adults



                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      32]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                          Computer Literacy Program for Barangay         Barangay Officials
                                                          Officials
                                                    (MS Office Tutorials)

                                          Computer Literacy Program for Barangay         Barangay Officials
                                                          Officials
                                                    (MS Office Tutorials)

                                          Computer Literacy Program for Barangay         Barangay Officials
                                                          Officials
                                                    (MS Office Tutorials)

                                          Computer Literacy Program for Barangay         Barangay Officials
                                                          Officials
                                                    (MS Office Tutorials)













































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  The extension program is sustainable.

                     EXTENSION              TARGET YEAR OF             STATUS OF           NO. OF TRAINEES
                PROGRAM/ACTIVITIES          IMPLEMENTATION          IMPLEMENTATION              TRAINED
                    Microsoft Office               2020                 Conducted                  20
                   Application (Excel)
               Training to ALS Students
                    Microsoft Office               2020                 Conducted                  25
                   Application (Word)
               Training to ALS Students
                    Basic Computer                 2018                 Conducted                  15
                  Troubleshooting and
                     Maintenance
               Graphic Design and Basic            2018                 Conducted                  20
                       Animation
                    Basic Computer                 2018                 Conducted                  20
                  Troubleshooting and
                     Maintenance
                   Computer Literacy               2017                 Conducted                  10
                 Program for Barangay
                        Officials
                  (MS Office Tutorials)

                   Computer Literacy               2017                 Conducted                  10
                 Program for Barangay
                        Officials
                  (MS Office Tutorials)

                   Computer Literacy               2017                 Conducted                  10
                 Program for Barangay
                        Officials
                  (MS Office Tutorials)

                   Computer Literacy               2017                 Conducted                  10
                 Program for Barangay
                        Officials
                  (MS Office Tutorials)


















                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      34]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                             Sustainability Plan for BAGTAS with CvSU-Tanza Extension Program
                                                            2018-2020
               Human Resources
                  Sustainability factors        Sustainability Objective           Sustainability Actions
               Provision of extension staff,     Provide staff and             Hold regular comprehensive
               staff training and expertise      community stakeholders           staff training and preparation
               building                          training to support strategic    on key sustainability factors
                                                 planning skills, knowledge     Conduct regular training for
                                                 of needs assessment,             the stakeholders of the
                                                 leadership skills and fund       community
                                                 raising expertise
               Project Design and Implementation
                  Sustainability factors        Sustainability Objective           Sustainability Actions
               Project Proposal                Design extension project        Use community-based
                                                 and activities according to      needs activities
                                                 the needs of the community    Utilize community-based
                                                 (demand-driven)                  participatory principles in
                                               Design additional projects        choosing strategies and
                                                 based on the research            approach
                                                 results conducted by the
                                                 extension staff/faculty
                                                 members
               Financial Resources and Strategies
                  Sustainability factors        Sustainability Objective           Sustainability Actions
               Adequate funds/Outsourcing    Attain multiple sources of        Work  closely with
               of funds                          funding                          community partners to assist
                                               Recruit and engage                them in writing grants to fund
                                                 volunteers                       companion efforts
                                                                                Recruit and engage
                                                                                  community volunteers







               Demonstrate Effectiveness
                  Sustainability factors        Sustainability Objective           Sustainability Actions
               Document success and            Evaluate project                Design and implement a
               disseminate evidence to the       effectiveness                    comprehensive evaluation
               community                       Disseminate results to the        plan to assess the impact of
                                                 community                        the project implemented
                                                                                Hold regular dissemination
                                                                                  meetings with the
                                                                                  stakeholders/community to
                                                                                  disseminate the results of
                                                                                  the project and build
                                                                                  recognition success


                 The Department disseminates technology to the target clientele through the following delivery
                   system:




                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE





                                                                          Technology              Date and
                         Lecture                    Clientele
                                                                         Disseminated             Location
               Computer Literacy Classes to    4P’s members, out-      Skills on how to use      ON-GOING
                      ALS Students            of-school youths and     computer and other      Bagtas, Tanza,
                                                     adults                application             Cavite
                Microsoft Office Application   4P’s members, out-      Skills on how to use    February 6 and
                  (Excel) Training to ALS      of-school children,     computer and other         11, 2020
                         Students              youths and adults           application         Bagtas, Tanza,
                                                                                                   Cavite
                Microsoft Office Application   4P’s members, out-      Skills on how to use    February 20 and
                  (Word) Training to ALS       of-school children,     computer and other         27, 2020
                         Students              youths and adults           application         Bagtas, Tanza,
                                                                                                   Cavite
                     Basic Computer            4P’s members, out-    Skills on how to repair    May 11, 2018
                   Troubleshooting and         of-school children,      and troubleshoot       Bagtas, Tanza,
                       Maintenance             youths and adults       computer problems           Cavite
                Graphic Design and Basic       4P’s members, out-       Skills on graphic        May 4, 2018
                        Animation               of-school children      design and basic       Bagtas, Tanza,
                                                                           animation.              Cavite
                     Basic Computer            4P’s members, out-    Skills on how to repair    April 20, 2018
                   Troubleshooting and          of-school children      and troubleshoot       Bagtas, Tanza,
                       Maintenance                                     computer problems           Cavite
               Computer Literacy Program       Barangay Officials      Skills on how to use   October 28, 2017
                  for Barangay Officials                               computer and other      Bagtas, Tanza,
                   (MS Office Tutorials)                                   application             Cavite

               Computer Literacy Program       Barangay Officials      Skills on how to use   October 27, 2017
                  for Barangay Officials                               computer and other      Bagtas, Tanza,
                   (MS Office Tutorials)                                   application             Cavite

               Computer Literacy Program       Barangay Officials      Skills on how to use   October 21, 2017
                  for Barangay Officials                               computer and other      Bagtas, Tanza,
                   (MS Office Tutorials)                                   application             Cavite

               Computer Literacy Program       Barangay Officials      Skills on how to use   October 20, 2017
                  for Barangay Officials                               computer and other      Bagtas, Tanza,
                   (MS Office Tutorials)                                   application             Cavite

















                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      36]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  There is an extension instrument for monitoring and evaluation of extension activities.

























































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT




























































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      38]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT




























































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      39]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE





                      There is feedback/evaluation mechanism from stakeholders/beneficiaries/clientele utilized
                       to improve the delivery system of extension service.





















































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      40]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                      There is feedback/evaluation mechanism from stakeholders/beneficiaries/clientele utilized
                       to improve the delivery system of extension service.

                                                                       FEEDBACK EVALUATION FROM THE
                           EXTENSION ACTIVITY
                                                                                    CLIENTELE
                  Microsoft Office Application Training to ALS     The Extension Services Unit and Department of
                                February 2020                      Information Technology of CvSU- Tanza Campus
                                                                   continued the computer literacy program to high
                                                                   ALS  students  as  part  of  the  program.  This
                                                                   program aims to help the ALS students to acquire
                                                                   skills  on  how  to  use  computer  and  other
                                                                   application.    Out  of  45  participants,  only  40
                                                                   evaluated  the  remedial  program.  In  terms  of
                                                                   lecture, 66 percent of the participants rated it as
                                                                   excellent and 34 percent rated it as very good. In
                                                                   terms  of  timeliness  of  the  topic,  77%  of  the
                                                                   participants  rated  it  excellent  and  23%  rated  it
                                                                   very good. With respect to the lecturer, 88% rated
                                                                   it  excellent  and  12%  rated  it  very  good.  As  an
                                                                   over-all  ratings  of  the  training,  93%  rated  it  as
                                                                   excellent and 7% rated it very good.

                                                                   After  the  training,  the  campus  monitor  the
                                                                   progress  of  their  grades  through  the  ALS
                                                                   Teacher-in-Charge from Dep-Ed and it found out
                                                                   that  there  has  been  a  positive  improvement  in
                                                                   their academic performance.

              Basic Computer Troubleshooting and Maintenance       The Extension Services Unit and Department of
                          April 20 and May 11, 2018                Information Technology of CvSU- Tanza Campus
                                                                   continued the computer literacy program to 4P’s
                                                                   members through a series of training about basic
                                                                   computer  trouble  shooting  and  maintenance.
                                                                   This  program  aims  to  help  the  4P’s  members
                                                                   acquire skills on how to troubleshoot and repair
                                                                   computer.    Out  of  35  participants,  only  33
                                                                   evaluated  the  remedial  program.  In  terms  of
                                                                   lecture, 90 percent of the participants rated it as
                                                                   excellent and 10 percent rated it as very good. In
                                                                   terms  of  timeliness  of  the  topic,  93%  of  the
                                                                   participants rated it excellent and 7% rated it very
                                                                   good. With respect to the lecturer, 87% rated it
                                                                   excellent and 13% rated it very good. As an over-
                                                                   all ratings of the training, 93% rated it as excellent
                                                                   and 7% rated it very good.
                     Graphic Design and Basic Animation            The Extension Services Unit and Department of
                                 May 4, 2018                       Information Technology of CvSU- Tanza Campus
                                                                   continued the computer literacy program to 4P’s
                                                                   members  through  a  series  of  training  about
                                                                   graphic  design  and  basic  animation.  This
                                                                   program aims to help the 4P’s members acquire
                                                                   skills on graphic design and basic animation.  Out
                                                                   of 20 participants, only 18 evaluated the remedial
                                                                   program. In terms of lecture, 88 percent of the
                                                                   participants rated it as excellent and 12 percent



                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      41]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                                                   rated it as very good. In terms of timeliness of the
                                                                   topic,  94%  of  the  participants  rated  it  excellent
                                                                   and 6% rated it very good. With respect to the
                                                                   lecturer, 94% rated it excellent and 6% rated it
                                                                   very good. As an over-all ratings of the training,
                                                                   94%  rated  it  as  excellent  and  6%  rated  it  very
                                                                   good.

               Computer Literacy Program for Barangay Officials    To assess the improvements of the trainees after
                             (MS Office Tutorials)                 the  extension  activity,  interviews  were  done  to
                                October 2017                       the  Barangay  Chairperson.  As  a  result  of  the
                                                                   efforts  of  the  extension  program  to  help  them
                                                                   acquire  the  necessary  skills  on  how  to  use
                                                                   computer and other Microsoft office application,
                                                                   these barangay officials are now skilled in terms
                                                                   of using computer and has increase productivity
                                                                   based  from  the  Barangay  Chairperson  and
                                                                   attested by the Human Resource Officer of the
                                                                   barangay.



























































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      42]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                II.  OUTCOMES

                  The  Extension  Program  is  well  –  planned,  implemented,  monitored,  evaluated  and
                    disseminated.

















































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      43]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                                Republic of the Philippines
                                              CAVITE STATE UNIVERSITY
                                                      Tanza Campus
                                     Ph. 2, Bahay Katuparan, Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite
                                                    (046) 235 – 7997
                                                    www.cvsu.edu.ph


                                            EXTENSION PROJECT PROPOSAL


                I. Project Description

                  Title           :   BAGTAS with CvSU-Tanza

                                      (Bagtas ay Aasenso at Giginhawa kung Tayo Ay Sama-sama with
                                      CvSU -Tanza)
                  Location        :   Brgy. Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite

                  Proponent       :   Cavite State University – Tanza Campus

                  Beneficiaries  :    Out-of-school Children and Youth, Brgy. Officials, and non-working
                                         members of the community

                  Project Components:

                           Program 1:  Oplan Karunungan
                           Program 2:   Computer Literacy Program
                           Program 3:   Livelihood Programs for Non-Working Members of the Community

                           Program 4:   Health and Wellness

                  Partner Agencies:  Local Government Unit of the Municipality of Tanza, Cavite; Provincial
                                          Cooperative, Livelihood, and Entrepreneurial Development Office
                                          (PCLEDO); Farmers Training Center (FITS); Companies in Export
                                          Processing Zone Authority (EPZA)
                  Estimated Budget: Php 610,000

                  Duration        :   5 years

             II.   Rationale

                         The population explosion in Brgy. Bagtas has led to an initiative to alleviate poverty in the
                  barangay.    Brgy.  Bagtas,  having  the  most  number  of  populations  in  Tanza  (20,370  out  of
                  188,755), has been the site for relocation and reclamation.  However, people, who were displaced
                  out of their previous addresses, were relocated in the said barangay without having a regular
                  source of living.  Some of them could not find a decent job because they lack the educational and
                  other requirements for the job that they were applying for.  Others could not start any business
                  because they lack the skills in preparing innovative products that could help them earn additional
                  income for their families.






                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      44]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                         Thus, different extension activities are being proposed to increase the quality of life of the
                  citizens in the said barangay.  Non-formal education will help out-of-school children to be able to
                  read, write and count.  Also, livelihood programs deemed to strengthen housewives skills and at
                  the  same time,  augment the meager  income  of  their families.   In  addition,  awareness  drives
                  concerning health and other GAD-related issues are being proposed to inculcate the importance
                  of appropriate living condition for every member of the community.


             III.   Strategies of Implementation

                  A.  Formation of Committee
                             A committee was formed to study and gather benchmark information on the status,
                      needs, and conditions of selected communities in Tanza, Cavite during the second semester,
                      AY 2014 – 2015.  The committee was headed by the Extension Coordinator.  Two faculty
                      members from the different departments of the campus were selected as members of the
                      committee to ensure that the programs will conform to the mandate of the university.  The
                      committee used the following benchmark information, provided by Tanza Municipal Planning
                      and Development Office (TMPDO), in order to assess which group of individuals will be the
                      target beneficiaries of the proposal.

                             Table 1.  Data of Brgy. Bagtas population 2010 by sex, age, and employment
                                                               Male           Female           Total
                               Brgy. Bagtas Population        12,316           8,054          20,370
                               Age Bracket
                                         5 – 9                 1,453             951           2,404
                                        10 – 14                1,299             849           2,148
                                       OTHERS                  9,564           6,254          15,818
                               Enrolment Data
                                   Pre-School (3 – 6)          1,213             878           2,091
                                  Elementary (7 – 12)          1,176             823           1,999
                               Employment Data
                                       Employed                6,908           4,517          11,425
                                      Unemployed                 600             393             993
                                 Not in the labor force        4,808           3,144           7,952
                             Source: Philippine Statistics Authority and Tanza Municipal Planning and Development Office

                             The committee used the descriptive design of a study. Data utilized in the study mainly
                      came from the responses on the self-administered survey questions that were distributed to
                      the residents of Brgy. Bagtas.  Residents were selected using simple random sampling.

                             Results revealed that:

                                  87.14% of the residents perceived that they lack regular sources of living in the
                                    barangay because most (48.15%) of them lack the educational requirements
                                    and some (38.99%) lack the technical skills to either start a small business or
                                    to apply for a regular job;

                                  47.06%  of  the  residents  believed  that  these  problems  and  issues  may  be
                                    addressed through conduct of free seminars/trainings on livelihood programs;





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      45]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                                  18.33% of the residents suggested to conduct free seminar on candle making;
                                    17.33% suggested soap making; 15.33% suggested delicacy preparation such
                                    as yema, ube, leche flan, puto, and others; 13.67% suggested dishwashing
                                    liquid making; 13.00% suggested recycling of plastic products and water lily
                                    bags; while the remaining 8.67% suggested perfume-making;

                                  46.50% of the residents said that they have baking and cooking skills and they
                                    are willing to undergo trainings for delicacy preparation; also 22.50% reiterated
                                    that they  have  the  skills  in  the  arts  and trades and  that they  are  willing  to
                                    undergo trainings on preparation of innovative products such as candle, soap,
                                    and dishwashing liquid;


                  B.  Preparation of Proposal
                             The proposal to conduct extension programs in the community was based upon the
                      respondent’s needs and interests that are consistent with the goals of the campus and that
                      have been identified through surveys.

                             Some  programs  relative  to  the  needs  and  interests  of  the  residents  were  not
                      considered due to insufficiencies on facilities and absence of qualified faculty members to
                      handle  such  programs.  This  includes  recycling  of  plastic  products,  water  lily  bags,  and
                      perfume-making which may require raw materials that are unavailable from the community.

                             While  having  consultative  meetings  with  the  local  government  of  the  concerned
                      barangay, some requests to the university were raised.  First, the campus will have to offer
                      computer literacy program for their barangay officials.  This program aims to extend computer
                      literacy to the Brgy. officials, who, based on observation, lack with sufficient skills in computer
                      manipulation and processes. The LGU believes that technical skills must be manifested by
                      their officials to better serve their constituents.

                             Also, the LGU requested that the proponents offer literacy skills development among
                      their children.  According to them, a number of children were not enrolled in a formal school
                      and parents of these children affirm that they could not send them in formal school due to lack
                      of financial resources, that although education is free in public schools, they could not provide
                      the requirements that their children must submit.

                             Another request from the LGU is that the proponent should give awareness campaigns
                      on different health issues.  According to them, the increase in the rate of patients with dengue
                      and AIDS/HIV in the province had been alarming them and the residents.  And because the
                      proponent  is  a  GAD  advocate,  GAD-related  issues  and  concerns  were  included  in  this
                      awareness campaign, such as Anti-Violence against Women and their Children (anti-VAWC),
                      sexual harassment among others.


                  C.  Meeting of the Committee
                             A meeting of the campus Committee on Curriculum and Instruction was conducted
                      on April 10, 2015 to deliberate on the proposed extension programs in the campus.








                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      46]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                             The following is the decision of the members of the committee:
                                        Total Number of Committee Members              :      15

                                        Total Number of Committee Members who
                                               were present                            :      15

                                        Total Number of Committee Members who
                                               were absent                             :      0

                                        Number of Members in favor of the
                                               proposal                                :      15

                                        Number of Members not in favor of the
                                               proposal                                :      0


                             With this result, the following resolutions were passed by the Committee:

                             Resolution No. 3, s. 2015
                                    “Approving  the  extension  project  proposal  to  alleviate  poverty  in  Barangay
                             Bagtas with the following components: (1) Oplan Karunungan; (2) Computer Literacy
                             for Brgy. Officials; (3) Livelihood Programs for the citizens of Brgy. Bagtas; and (4)
                             Health  and  Wellness;  subject  to  the  endorsement  of  the  University  Administrative
                             Council and approval of the University Board of Regents.

                             Resolution No. 4, s. 2015

                                    “Approving the name of the extension project proposal to be BAGTAS with
                             CvSU-Tanza (Bagtas ay Aasenso at Giginhawa kung Tayo Ay Sama-sama
                             with  CvSU  -Tanza)  subject  to  the  endorsement  of  the  University  Administrative
                             Council and approval of the University Board of Regents.”
                  D.  Memorandum of Agreement
                             A  Memorandum  of  Agreement  (MOA)  will  be  drafted  and  signed  by  different
                      stakeholders involved in the conduct of such extension programs.  Stakeholders such as Local
                      Government Unit of the municipality of Tanza, Cavite; Provincial Cooperative, Livelihood, and
                      Entrepreneurial Development Office (PCLEDO); Farmers Training Center (FITS); Companies
                      in Export Processing Zone Authority (EPZA); and others.

                  E.  Actual Implementation
                             All the extension programs under this project will be spearheaded by the campus dean
                      and  will  be  facilitated  by  faculty  members  and  students  in  their  respective  area  of
                      specialization.  Since this is an extension project, voluntary participation among faculty and
                      students will be encouraged.  Additional funds for the project proposal will be sought through
                      donations  from  the  Local  Government  Unit  of  Brgy.  Bagtas,  Tanza,  Cavite  and  other
                      concerned  citizens  and  government  and  non-government  agencies,  such  as  but  are  not
                      limited  to,  Provincial  Cooperative,  Livelihood,  and  Entrepreneurial  Development  Office
                      (PCLEDO); Farmers Training Center (FITS); Companies in Export Processing Zone Authority
                      (EPZA); and others.








                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      47]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                         Program 1: Oplan Karunungan
                         1.  All BSE students and faculty members under the Teacher Education Department are
                             enjoined to take part in this program.
                         2.  The program will be done during Fridays and Saturdays, 7:30 a.m. to 9:30 a.m.at Rm.
                             102 of the Cavite State University – Tanza Campus.
                         3.  The BSE students and faculty members will have their own schedule on when to share
                             their knowledge and teaching skills among the out-of-school youths.
                         4.  For security purposes, each participant will wear name tags during each session to
                             recognize them as part of the program.
                         5.  On the first day of the session, each participant will undergo a pre-assessment to
                             determine their basic literacy and numeracy skills.
                         6.  The officers will coordinate with the Barangay Captain to recommend and/or suggest
                             viable participants of this program.
                         7.  For the first year of implementation, at least 10 out-of-school youths will be the target
                             participants.
                         8.  Assigned members will see to it that cleanliness and orderliness of the said classroom
                             will be maintained during the session.
                         9.  The  teachers  and  student-teachers  will  select  three  best  students  to  be  awarded
                             during the Recognition Program.
                         10. Every participant will be awarded Certificate of Completion upon finishing the
                             program.
                         11. After the program, each participants will undergo a post-assessment to determine the
                             effect of the intervention that was conducted.
                         12. Students who have finished the program will be encouraged and supported to enroll
                             in a formal elementary school.

                         Program 2: Computer Literacy Program
                         1.  All  BSIT  students  and  faculty  members  under  the  Department  of  Information
                             Technology are enjoined to take part in this program.
                         2.  The program will be done during Fridays and Saturdays, 8:30 a.m. to 10:30 a.m. at
                             Computer Laboratory of the Cavite State University – Tanza Campus.
                         3.  The BSIT students and faculty members will have their own schedule on when to share
                             their knowledge and teaching skills among the barangay officials.
                         4.  For security purposes, each participant will wear name tags during each session to
                             recognize them as part of the program.
                         5.  The officers will coordinate with the Barangay Captain to recommend and/or suggest
                             viable participants of this program.
                         6.  For the first year of implementation, at least 10 selected barangay officials, and 4P’s
                             members will be taught of basic computer skills during the time allotted.
                         7.  Assigned members will see to it that cleanliness and orderliness of the said classroom
                             will be maintained during the session.
                         8.  The teachers and student-teachers will select three best participants to be awarded
                             during the Recognition Program.
                         9.  Every participant will be awarded Certificate of Completion upon finishing the
                             program.
                         10. As part of the monitoring and evaluation of the program, each participant will undergo
                             a pre- and post-test to determine whether they have achieved the basic skills that are
                             expected of them.

                         Program 3: Livelihood Programs
                         1.  All  BSBM  and  BSHRM  students  and  faculty  members  under  the  Department  of
                             Management are enjoined to take part in this program and will be the facilitators and
                             over-all in-charge.





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      48]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                         2.  The program will be done during Fridays and Saturdays, 7:30 a.m. to 9:30 a.m. at
                             Function Hall of the Cavite State University – Tanza Campus.
                         3.  The officers will coordinate with the Barangay Captain to recommend and/or suggest
                             viable participants of this program.
                         4.  Assistance  from  the  Provincial  Cooperative,  Livelihood,  and  Entrepreneurial
                             Development Office (PCLEDO) will be sought in terms of training of participants.
                         5.  At least 20 housewives will be invited to take part in each session.
                         6.  All participants must be residents of Brgy. Bagtas as certified and referred by the LGU
                             officials.
                         7.  Participants  with  outstanding  performance  in  selected  activities  will  be  rewarded
                             accordingly.  They will be given small amount of money to start their own business.
                         8.  Every participant will be awarded Certificate of Completion upon finishing the program.
                         9.  As part of the monitoring and evaluation of the program, each participant will undergo
                             a pre- and post-test to determine whether they have achieved the basic skills that are
                             expected of them.

                         Program 4: Health and Wellness
                         1.  All students and members of the Sports Club of the campus, and faculty members are
                             enjoined to take part in this program.
                         2.  The  Aerobics/Zumba  session  will  be  done  every  Wednesday,  starting  January  to
                             March 2016 thru the initiative of a competitive professional dance instructor. Summer
                             Sports Clinic and Sports fest with the community will be held every weekend starting
                             March to June 2016.  Continuous awareness drive on health issues will be held every
                             Friday  and  Saturday,  starting  January  to  March  2016.   Awareness  drive  on  GAD-
                             related concerns will be held every Wednesday, starting January to March 2016.
                         3.  The officers will coordinate with the Barangay Captain to recommend and/or suggest
                             viable participants of this program.  Also, they will be requested to lend a venue for
                             the program.
                         4.  At least 20 housewives will be invited to take part in the aerobics/Zumba session. Out-
                             of-school youths will be the target participants in the summer sports clinic and sports
                             fest with the community.  At least 30 residents will be the target participants in the
                             awareness drive on health and GAD-related issues.
                         5.  All participants must be residents of Brgy. Bagtas as certified and referred by the LGU
                             officials.
                         6.  Participants  with  outstanding  performance  in  selected  activities  will  be  rewarded
                             accordingly, especially those who exceled in sports and other recreational activities.
                         7.  Every participant will be awarded Certificate of Completion upon finishing the program.
                         8.  As part of the monitoring and evaluation of the program, each participant will undergo
                             a pre- and post-test to determine whether they have achieved the basic skills that are
                             expected of them.

                  F.  Monitoring and Evaluation
                             Each program will undergo three evaluations: before, during, and after conduct of each
                      evaluation.  On the first week of each session, each participant will undergo a pre-assessment
                      to determine their current status in the program they were registered to. Evaluation during the
                      conduct  of  the  program  will  also  be  done  in  order  to  identify  problems  arising  and  to
                      immediately resolve these problems. Post-assessment will be done in order to determine if
                      they  have  achieved  the  basic  skills  that  are  expected  of  them.    This  will  also  determine
                      whether the program is successful and has delivered significant impact to the community.







                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      49]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


             IV.  Budgetary Allocation (5 years)
                                       PARTICULARS/PROGRAM                                 AMOUNT (PhP)

                    Program 1: Oplan Karunungan                                               60,000.00
                    Program 2: Computer Literacy Program                                      45,000.00

                    Program 3: Livelihood Programs for Non-Working Members                    300,000.00
                    of the Community
                    Program 4: Health and Wellness                                           205,000.00

                                              TOTAL                                             610,000.00

             V.   Source of Fund
                         The main source of fund of the project will be the campus budget for extension.  The
                  project proponent will solicit additional funding from the Local Government Unit of Tanza and
                  other partner NGO’s and GO’s such as, but not limited to, Provincial Cooperative, Livelihood, and
                  Entrepreneurial Development Office (PCLEDO); Farmers Training Center (FITS); and Companies
                  in Export Processing Zone Authority (EPZA).









































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      50]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  The extension program has contributed to the improvement on the quality of life of the target
                    clientele/beneficiaries.

             MANIFESTATIONS THAT EXTENSION PROGRAMS/PROJECTS HAVE CONTRIBUTED TO THE
                      IMPROVEMENT OF THE QUALITY OF LIFE OF THE CLIENT/BENEFICIARIES

                 EXTENSION ACTIVITY                    OBJECTIVES                      IMPLICATIONS
               Computer Literacy Classes to    Help the residents of Barangay  Alternative  Learning  System
                      ALS Students             Bagtas  particularly  the  out-of- classes  will  help  the  out-of-
                       ON-GOING                school youths and out-of-school  school youths and out-of-school
                                               adults  finished  their  secondary  adults  finished  their  secondary
                                               education.                       education.
                Microsoft Office Application   Help the residents of Barangay  Alternative  Learning  System
              Training to ALS February 2020  Bagtas  particularly  the  out-of- classes  will  help  the  out-of-
                                               school youths and out-of-school  school youths and out-of-school
                                               adults  finished  their  secondary  adults  finished  their  secondary
                                               education.                       education.
                     Basic Computer            Help the residents of barangay  This  extension  activity  helped
                   Troubleshooting and         particularly  the  4P’s  members  the 4P’s members acquire skills
                       Maintenance             to  have  additional  source  of  on  how  to  troubleshoot  and
                April 20 and May 11, 2018      income  and  to  improve  their  repair computer.
                                               socio-economic status.
                Graphic Design and Basic       Help the residents of barangay  This  extension  activity  helped
                        Animation              particularly  the  4P’s  members  the 4P’s members acquire skills
                       May 4, 2018             to  have  additional  source  of  on  graphic  design  and  basic
                                               income  and  to  improve  their  animation.
                                               socio-economic status.
              Computer Literacy Program for  Help  the  barangay  officials  This  extension  activity  helped
                    Barangay Officials         acquire the necessary skills on  the  out-of-school  children  to
                   (MS Office Tutorials)       how to use computer and other  read and write and now enrolled
                      October 2017             Microsoft office application.    in public schools.

























                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      51]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                                                  GERALDINE D. QUINES

                   (ONE OF THE BENEFICIARIES OF COMPUTER LITERACY CLASSES FOR 4P’S MEMBERS)






























                          The computer literacy classes helped Ms. Quines passed the ALS exam and
                                                  now a student of the campus








             Prepared by:


             RITCH M. BANATE
             Extension Coordinator









                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      52]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE




                III.  BEST PRACTICES

                  The administration, faculty of Department of Information Technology and other stakeholders
                    participates in the planning and organization of the extension programs;

                  The administration, faculty of the Department of Information Technology and its students are
                    involved in the implementation and dissemination of extension program;

                  The extension program serves varied clienteles.

                  Technologies  and  knowledge  are  disseminated  to  the  target  clients  through  appropriate
                    extension delivery systems;

                  The extension project is sustainable;

                  There is a system of monitoring and evaluation of the extension activities;

                  The extension project objective is to create a positive impact for the community; and

                  Accomplishment reports are submitted on time.
























































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      53]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


             PARAMETER C – FUNDING AND OTHER RESOURCES

                I.  SYSTEM-INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                  There  is  an  approved  financial  plan  for  2017  –  2020  showing  the  approved  budgets  for
                    extension program for each respective year.

                    The allocated budget for Tanza Campus’ Extension Program is shown in the next table. This

             budget is allocated to the extension activities of BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza Extension Program.


                                                                 Amount in Peso
                      Item
                                         2017               2018                2019                2020

              Budgetary Allocation    110,000.00         124,267.50         158, 415.00         248, 062.50






























































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      54]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT



























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      55]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      56]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT




























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      57]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                       There are facilities for the Extension Program
























                                Mr. Ritch M. Banate, the extension coordinator of Tanza Campus



















                                  The classrooms for Computer Literacy classes and trainings











                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      58]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                  There are Institutional policies on deloading/equivalent teaching load for extension.

                                                              Rule V
                                              Terms and Conditions of Employment

                    Article 12. Specific Policies and Guidelines on Faculty Workload

                    Section 2.  Maximum Workload and Overload Compensation

                           The maximum regular teaching load of an academic full – time teaching staff without
                    administrative and supervisory assignment in any given semester shall be 18 teaching hours
                    (TCH) per week. (TCH) and equivalent WL units shall be reduced to 18 and 25, respectively
                    effective First Semester, AY 2004 – 2005 depending on availability of funds). For purposes of
                    overload pay, this is equivalent to the maximum of 25 instruction workload (WL) credit units.

                        a.  The regular workload of full–time teaching staff in a given  semester shall include only
                            those related to instruction,  administrative  assignments  and  other  services  duly
                            supported by designations issued by the Office of the President of the University (OUP)
                            as recommended by the vice president concerned.

                        b.  Faculty  members  who  opt  to  be  on  full-time  teaching  but  who  conduct  important
                            projects under the priority commodity thrusts of the University shall earn credit units for
                            those projects based on the guidelines for  research  and  extension  workload.  This
                            credit unit shall be added to  instruction workload provided that these credit units are
                            not credited on full-time research.

                        c.  The final report on faculty workload, including the   summary   thereof,   shall   be
                            submitted to the office of the Vice   President  for  Academic  Affairs  for  consolidation
                            within the final examination period of every semester.
                        d.  An academic staff who is unable to reach the maximum teaching load per week shall
                            be required to teach other courses in other units of the University and/or render  other
                            services  deemed  necessary  as  recommended  by  the  Vice  President  for  Academic
                            Affairs and approved by the  University President in order to reach the mandatory 40-
                            hour service per week required of all government   personnel.    In  no  case,  however,
                            shall the conduct of   other  services  lead  to  hiring  of  additional  part-time  or  full-time
                            faculty member. Hiring will only be done when all   faculty members are fully loaded at
                            18 TCH each per week. Exemptions to the required 18 TCH, are faculty members with
                            management  and  supervisory  designations  specified.  The  assigning  of  such  other
                            services shall be endorsed by the Vice President of Academic Affairs for  approval  by
                            the University President.

                        e.  In  case faculty  members  carrying  the full  load of  18 TCH  are given  extra teaching
                            assignment scheduled outside the official time, such assignment shall be covered by a
                            job order in order for the faculty member to receive equitable remuneration.

                        f.  The detailed guidelines for faculty workload system shall   be prepared, reviewed and
                            revised  periodically  by  the  Academic  Council  taking  into  account  the  policies  listed
                            above.











                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      59]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                II.  IMPLEMENTATION
                  There is budgetary allocation for the Academic Unit’s Extension Program in the last 3 years.

                                    Financial Report on Extension Budget Utilization
                                                           EXTENSION                       EXPENSES
                                 Date
                                                     PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES                      (Php)
                       February 6 and 11, 2020      Microsoft Office Application            2,500.00
                                                      (Excel) Training to ALS
                                                             Students


                      February 20 and 27, 2020      Microsoft Office Application            2,650.50
                                                       (Word) Training to ALS
                                                             Students

                            May 11, 2018                  Basic Computer
                                                        Troubleshooting and                 3,020.75
                                                           Maintenance

                             May 4, 2018             Graphic Design and Basic               1,950.75
                                                             Animation

                            April 20, 2018                Basic Computer
                                                        Troubleshooting and                 2,365.50
                                                           Maintenance

                           October 28, 2017         Computer Literacy Program
                                                       for Barangay Officials               1,200.00
                                                        (MS Office Tutorials)

                           October 27, 2017         Computer Literacy Program
                                                       for Barangay Officials                990.50
                                                        (MS Office Tutorials)

                           October 21, 2017         Computer Literacy Program
                                                       for Barangay Officials               1,200.00
                                                        (MS Office Tutorials)

                           October 20, 2017         Computer Literacy Program
                                                       for Barangay Officials               2,650.75
                                                        (MS Office Tutorials)



             Cash on Hand    P20, 250.00
             Expenses       P18, 528.75
                           P 1, 721.25












                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      60]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  There are Extension Linkages.

                                                NAME OF
                TYPE OF LINKAGE                                         NATURE OF ASSISTANCE
                                         AGENCIES/LINKAGES
               Local                     Municipality of Tanza        Ensure Support in the
                                                                         implementation of the
                                                                         project;
                                                                       Help in sourcing out of funds,
                                                                         donations, grants for the
                                                                         project; and
                                                                       Provide various assistance in
                                                                         the conduct extension
                                                                         activities.

                                                                       Assist in the conduct of
                                         Barangay Bagtas, Tanza,        community needs
                                          Cavite                         assessment in the barangay
                                                                         as part of planning;
                                                                       Assist in the implementation
                                                                         of extension activities based
                                                                         on community diagnosis;
                                                                       Assist in the monitoring and
                                                                         evaluation of the project;
                                                                       Ensure the participation of
                                                                         the target clienteles;
                                                                       Provide support in the
                                                                         implementation of the
                                                                         projects;
                                                                       Help in sourcing out of funds,
                                                                         donations, grants for the
                                                                         projects; and
                                                                       Provide assistance in the
                                                                         implementation of the
                                                                         projects.
               National                  Provincial Government –      Provision of funds
                                          Environment and Natural    Identify and provide the exact
                                          Resources Office               location of the adopted
                                                                         streambank area.
                                                                       Closely coordinate with the
                                                                         community in the
                                                                         development of a detailed
                                                                         implementation schemes to
                                                                         make sure that interventions
                                                                         are effectively and efficiently
                                                                         undertaken.















                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      61]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                III.  OUTCOMES

                  Extension Program is adequately funded.

             The allocated budget for Tanza Campus’ Extension Program is shown in the next table. This budget is

             allocated to the extension activities of BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza Extension Program.


                                                                 Amount in Peso
                      Item
                                         2017               2018                2019                2020

              Budgetary Allocation    110,000.00         124,267.50         158, 415.00         248, 062.50


































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      62]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT



























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      63]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      64]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE






































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      65]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                IV. BEST PRACTICES

                  The  university  allocates  budget  to  the  Extension  Services  Unit  for  the  extension
                    programs/projects/activities;

                  There are linkages that support the extension program either by participation or monetary;

                  There is a budget allocation on each of the extension activities;
                  There are suitable facilities and equipment such as internet and ICT resources for extension
                    activities; and

                  There is a guideline for honoraria and other incentives for the faculty involved in extension
                    activities.














































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      66]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT




             PARAMETER D – COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT AND PARTICIPATION

                I.  SYSTEM – INPUTS AND PROCESSES

                      There  are  strategies  to  Involve  community,  government  and  private  agencies  in  the
                       Extension Program is evident.
                              STRATEGIES                                  INDIVIDUALS INVOLVED
                         Communication through:                       Extension unit and the community,
                              Text messages                     Extension unit and the speakers/lecturers from
                          Verbal Communication                        government and private agencies
                              Telephone calls
                              Invitation letter
                               Cooperation                     Cooperation among experts in specific discipline
                                                                 Cooperation among the extensionists and the
                                                                community by attending seminars, lectures and
                                                                               demonstrations
                               Coordination                      Extension Coordinators coordinate with other
                                                                 campuses when a community need is not an
                                                                           expertise of the campus
                                                                 Coordination with other government agencies
                               Collaboration                     Partnerships with other organization through
                                                                 sharing of knowledge, technology, skills and
                                                                                  resources
                                                                  Collaboration with the community through
                                                                             sharing of resources
                               Convergence                      Strong convergence with other stakeholders for
                                                                  the effective planning, implementation and
                                                                       monitoring of extension activities
                


                II.  IMPLEMENTATION

                  Community  participation  in  the  planning,  implementation,  monitoring  and  evaluation,  fund-
                    sourcing and technology/knowledge utilizations.

                           The residents and beneficiaries of the extension programs of the campus are already
                    involved in the planning stage of BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza and Oplan Karunungan of the
                    Teacher Education Department. Consultative meetings are regularly conducted to ensure the
                    success of the program and to incorporate the feedback of the stakeholders.
                           There is a Memorandum of Agreement between the LGU of Tanza and Barangay Bagtas
                    and they are always committed to provide assistance by coordinating with different government
                    and  non-government  unit  to  help  the  Campus  with  its  extension  projects.  They  are  also
                    providing school supplies to be used by the students of Oplan Karunungan.










                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      67]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                  The community participates and are involved in extension activities.

                                                                      PERSONS INVOLVED
                      Date         Title of Activity
                                                      Administration      Faculty      Students     Clientele
                   ON-GOING           Computer         Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      BYTES       Students
                                       Literacy           Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers    Community
                                   Classes to ALS                       Ritch M.         and          (4P’s
                                       Students                         Banate        Selected IT   members,
                                                                        Joyce Erika    Students       out-of-
                                                                        S. Senaris                    school
                                                                        Cris Albert                  children,
                                                                        P. Cajigas                 youths and
                                                                        Debbie                       adults)
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine
                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                 February 6 and    Microsoft Office    Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      BYTES       Students
                    11, 2020          Application         Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers    Community
                                   (Excel) Training                     Ritch M.         and          (4P’s
                                        to ALS                          Banate        Selected IT   members,
                                       Students                         Joyce Erika    Students       out-of-
                                                                        S. Senaris                    school
                                                                        Cris Albert                  children,
                                                                        P. Cajigas                 youths and
                                                                        Debbie                       adults)
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine
                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                 February 20 and  Microsoft Office     Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      BYTES       Students
                    27, 2020          Application         Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers    Community
                                   (Word) Training                      Ritch M.         and          (4P’s
                                        to ALS                          Banate        Selected IT   members,
                                       Students                         Joyce Erika    Students       out-of-
                                                                        S. Senaris                    school
                                                                        Cris Albert                  children,
                                                                        P. Cajigas                 youths and
                                                                        Debbie                       adults)
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine






                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      68]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                  May 11, 2018     Basic Computer      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      BYTES          4P’s
                                   Troubleshooting        Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers     members,
                                         and                            Ritch M.         and          out-of-
                                     Maintenance                        Banate        Selected IT     school
                                                                        Joyce Erika    Students      children,
                                                                        S. Senaris                 youths and
                                                                        Cris Albert                   adults
                                                                        P. Cajigas
                                                                        Debbie
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine
                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                   May 4, 2018     Graphic Design      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      BYTES          4P’s
                                      and Basic           Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers     members,
                                      Animation                         Ritch M.         and          out-of-
                                                                        Banate        Selected IT     school
                                                                        Joyce Erika    Students      children,
                                                                        S. Senaris                 youths and
                                                                        Cris Albert                   adults
                                                                        P. Cajigas
                                                                        Debbie
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine
                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                  April 20, 2018   Basic Computer      Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      BYTES          4P’s
                                   Troubleshooting        Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers     members,
                                         and                            Ritch M.         and          out-of-
                                     Maintenance                        Banate        Selected IT     school
                                                                        Joyce Erika    Students      children,
                                                                        S. Senaris                 youths and
                                                                        Cris Albert                   adults
                                                                        P. Cajigas
                                                                        Debbie
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine




                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      69]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                   October 28,        Computer         Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      COPE        Barangay
                      2017             Literacy           Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers      Officials
                                     Program for                        Ritch M.         and
                                      Barangay                          Banate         Selected
                                       Officials                        Joyce Erika       SE
                                      (MS Office                        S. Senaris     Students
                                      Tutorials)                        Cris Albert
                                                                        P. Cajigas
                                                                        Debbie
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine
                                                                        Dr. Noel B.
                                                                        Manarpiis
                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                   October 27,        Computer         Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      COPE        Barangay
                      2017             Literacy           Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers      Officials
                                     Program for                        Ritch M.         and
                                      Barangay                          Banate         Selected
                                       Officials                        Joyce Erika       SE
                                      (MS Office                        S. Senaris     Students
                                      Tutorials)                        Cris Albert
                                                                        P. Cajigas
                                                                        Debbie
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine
                                                                        Dr. Noel B.
                                                                        Manarpiis
                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                   October 21,        Computer         Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      COPE        Barangay
                      2017             Literacy           Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers      Officials
                                     Program for                        Ritch M.         and
                                      Barangay                          Banate         Selected
                                       Officials                        Joyce Erika       SE
                                      (MS Office                        S. Senaris     Students
                                      Tutorials)                        Cris Albert
                                                                        P. Cajigas





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      70]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                                                                        Debbie
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine
                                                                        Dr. Noel B.
                                                                        Manarpiis
                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo
                   October 20,        Computer         Prof. Noel A.    Mildred A.      COPE        Barangay
                      2017             Literacy           Sedigo        Sebastian      Officers      Officials
                                     Program for                        Ritch M.         and
                                      Barangay                          Banate         Selected
                                       Officials                        Joyce Erika       SE
                                      (MS Office                        S. Senaris     Students
                                      Tutorials)                        Cris Albert
                                                                        P. Cajigas
                                                                        Debbie
                                                                        Rose T.
                                                                        Banag
                                                                        Melona O.
                                                                        Igmasine
                                                                        Dr. Noel B.
                                                                        Manarpiis
                                                                        Mary Rose
                                                                        E.
                                                                        Elamparo,
                                                                        Mark Joel
                                                                        C. Sibulo


























                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      71]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


               The technology, knowledge learned, and skills acquired from the extension projects and activities
                 are utilized.



                                                      EXTENSION               UTILIZATION OF ACQUIRED
                    Date and Location
                                                 PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES                 TECHNOLOGY
                        ON-GOING              Computer Literacy Classes to    Skills on how to use computer
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite              ALS Students                 and other application
                  February 6 and 11, 2020      Microsoft Office Application   Skills on how to use computer
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite          (Excel) Training to ALS          and other application
                                                        Students
                 February 20 and 27, 2020      Microsoft Office Application   Skills on how to use computer
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite          (Word) Training to ALS           and other application
                                                        Students
                       May 11, 2018                  Basic Computer             Skills on how to repair and
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite           Troubleshooting and            troubleshoot computer
                                                       Maintenance                      problems
                        May 4, 2018             Graphic Design and Basic       Skills on graphic design and
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite                Animation                    basic animation.
                       April 20, 2018                Basic Computer             Skills on how to repair and
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite           Troubleshooting and            troubleshoot computer
                                                       Maintenance                      problems
                     October 28, 2017          Computer Literacy Program      Skills on how to use computer
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite          for Barangay Officials           and other application
                                                   (MS Office Tutorials)

                     October 27, 2017          Computer Literacy Program      Skills on how to use computer
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite          for Barangay Officials           and other application
                                                   (MS Office Tutorials)

                     October 21, 2017          Computer Literacy Program      Skills on how to use computer
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite          for Barangay Officials           and other application
                                                   (MS Office Tutorials)

                     October 20, 2017          Computer Literacy Program      Skills on how to use computer
                   Bagtas, Tanza, Cavite          for Barangay Officials           and other application
                                                   (MS Office Tutorials)




















                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      72]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


                  The Program’s commitment to the service of the community is as follows.

                    Rationale and Objectives of the BAGTAS with CvSU – Tanza

                    RATIONALE:
                           The population explosion in Brgy. Bagtas has led to an initiative to alleviate poverty in
                    the barangay.  Brgy. Bagtas, having the most number of populations in Tanza (20,370 out of
                    188,755),  has  been  the  site  for  relocation  and  reclamation.    However,  people,  who  were
                    displaced out of their previous addresses, were relocated in the said barangay without having
                    a regular source of living.  Some of them could not find a decent job because they lack the
                    educational and other requirements for the job that they were applying for.  Others could not
                    start any business because they lack the skills in preparing innovative products that could help
                    them earn additional income for their families.

                           Thus, different extension activities are being proposed to increase the quality of life of
                    the citizens in the said barangay.  Non-formal education will help out-of-school children to be
                    able to read, write and count.  Also, livelihood programs deemed to strengthen housewives
                    skills  and  at  the  same  time,  augment  the  meager  income  of  their  families.    In  addition,
                    awareness  drives  concerning  health  and  other  GAD-related  issues  are  being  proposed  to
                    inculcate the importance of appropriate living condition for every member of the community.
                           Extension activities are being proposed to increase the quality of life of the citizens in
                    Barangay Bagtas.

                         1.  Oplan Karunungan is a form of non-formal education which  will help out-of-school
                             children to be able to read, write, and count, and out-of-school youths and adults to
                             finish their secondary education.

                         2.  Computer Literacy Program will provide sufficient skills in computer manipulation and
                             processes to better serve the constituents of the barangay.

                         3.  Livelihood programs deemed to strengthen the skills of non-working members of the
                             community and at the same time, augment the meager income of their families.

                         4.  Awareness drives concerning health and other GAD-related issues will inculcate the
                             importance of the appropriate living condition for every member of the community.

                    OBJECTIVES:
                    The extension program is an initiative to alleviate poverty in Brgy. Bagtas, having the most
                    number of populations in Tanza and being the site for relocation and reclamation.

                       I.  Oplan Karunungan
                               1.  To appreciate the importance of literacy and numeracy among the participants,
                                  thereby persuading them to enroll in a formal school.
                               2.  To help the out-of-school youths and adults to finish their secondary education;

                                  and
                               3.  To  immerse  future  educators  in  the  teaching  process,  having  out-of-school
                                  youths as their students.

                       II.  Computer Literacy Program





                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      73]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                               1.  To extend computer literacy to the Brgy. Officials, who based on observation,
                                  lack with sufficient skills in computer manipulation and processes.

                               2.  To promote with the participants the following basic skills:
                                        Word processing using MS Word or other text editors Spreadsheet like

                                         MS Excel for automated calculations
                                        Scanning and Printing

                                        Emailing and instant messaging
                                        Scanning and Printing digital documents
                                        Burning CD or DVD

                               3.  To promote and enhance the use of technology tools, especially the use of MS
                                  Office applications and their benefits.


                       III.  Livelihood Programs
                               1.  To educate participants on how to start a small business.
                               2.  To educate participants on how that could help them generate additional income.
                               3.  To share with them some skills in preparing innovative products.
                               4.  To encourage them to start a business based on the products that they have
                                  learned to prepare.

                       IV. Health and Wellness
                               1.  To inculcate the importance of health and wellness among the participants.
                               2.  To develop spirit of camaraderie among participants through sports and other
                                  recreational activities.
                               3.  To promote continuous awareness on different health issues and concerns.


                  The College/Academic Unit is committed to the service and development of the community.
                           Commitment of the Teacher Education Department to the services and development of
                    the community is manifested in the Memorandum of Agreement between the stakeholders.






























                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      74]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      75]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT



























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      76]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT


























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      77]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT



























































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      78]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
















































































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      79]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                III.  OUTCOMES

                      There is wholesome coordination between the Extension implementers and the target
                       clientele/beneficiaries.


                                            COMPUTER LITERACY PROGRAM
































                                               The ALS students during their classes














                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      80]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT





































                       Ms. Mildred A. Sebastian during her computer literacy classes to 4P’s members


















                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      81]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT



































                                         ALS students during their digital literacy class




















                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      82]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE
































                    4P’s members during their training on basic computer troubleshooting and maintenance
























                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      83]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
                                                                                                      BSE
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT






































                          The participants and the facilitators during the Computer Literacy Program



















                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      84]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[PROGRAM PERFORMA
              Program Performance Profile                     NCE PROFILE           BSIT
                                                                                                      BSE


                IV. BEST PRACTICES

                  There are strategies to Involve community, government and private agencies in the Extension
                    Program is evident.
                  Community participation and involvement in extension activities;


                  The Department of Information Technology is committed to the service and development of the
                    community;

                  Community programs and services are coordinated with different stakeholders;

                  There is a Memorandum of Agreement between stakeholders.

                  There is a wholesome coordination of the Department with the stakeholders and the community;

                  The  technology,  knowledge  learned,  and  skills  acquired  from  the  extension  projects  and
                    activities are utilized; and

                  Proper documentation of the activities are exercised.



























































                        Area VI: Extension and Community Involvement                                      85]]></page></pages></Search>